hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and today we are going to see a new
topic in spring board that is Bean
Scopes
and here till now we have covered all
this topics and also all this green
which I have highlighted and today
dependency injection we have already
covered we have already seen Bean
everything it's life cycle and today I'm
covering the Scopes very important okay
so we have covered
here okay so let's start without any
wasting time so the first and foremost
what is the prerequisite to understand
the scope so you have to have the
understanding of bean and its life cycle
which we have covered in the previous
session so there I have told you this
Bean life cycle right this is the flow
it goes so this is very important to
understand the scope right why because
there are multiple different type of
Scopes single turn prototype request
session and also there are one more
application right so there are five
types of Scopes and generally if you
know this life cycle of a
bean it would be helpful for you to
picturize like
okay at what time the object is getting
created okay so please have a look at
this bean and life cycle before you jump
into the scope
video okay let's start with singl
ton so this is the default scope so here
consider this
classes this is the class we have
already seen you can create it as a rest
controller where you can define an API
like I have given get mapping we have
already seen that okay so does I have
defined any scope here no no scope I
have defined here so what would be the
default scope here single ton so what
does Singleton means only one instance
created per ioc what does that mean I
told you when you start an application
let's say when you start an application
you see that you will see web server
application context are started right so
that's actually your ioc is getting
started so only one instance created per
ioc right or you can say that in most of
the manner one instance per application
considering that one application is
running only one
ioc okay and one more thing if you
remember remember I told you that single
turn are eagerly initialized by
ioc and I have showed you the example of
eagerly and the lazy initialization also
while I was explaining you this life
cycle I have explained both eagerly and
lazy so single turn are eagerly
initialized let's see an example you
will recall it better so this is one
class very basic class I haven't defined
anything here no scope so what would be
the default single
turn this is another test controller to
but here if you see I can also do this
at theate scope you can do value equals
to like this configurable bean factory
do scope single turn so this is like
even though single turn is default uh is
single Turn Only I don't have to write
it but just for demo purpose that you
can also specifically write also in this
way so there is another class which I
write user which is a component and I
can write it like this also at there is
a scope and direct you can put a string
single turn right internally this enam
it's actually a string only single ter
right so anything whichever you like you
can use it
either you can use directly string or
enum or you don't do anything in all
manner it's this class is a single turn
class now what would happen when you
start the
application what would happen so if you
know the life cycle of a bean what would
happen is when you start the application
ioc started and when ioc started what it
will do is it will look for the
classes which need to be managed by
spring so it will look for at theate
component atate rest controller kind of
classes so it found this test controller
one first so what it will do is it will
call its Constructor test controller one
instance
initialization test controller one
initialization but this object is not
fully constructed yet as you know the
life cycle right for first it construct
a bean then it inject the dependency
then call Post
construct So
currently it created a bean but
dependencies are not
injected so now it will look for okay is
there any dependency yes user so now
user would be
invoked so user initialization will
happen here if you see second is user
initialization so user has any
dependency no no dependency so means
user now goes to the next life cycle
post construct user object created and
his hash code is this so one user object
is
created user object created so now let's
say
that user object got created with hash
code some 1 4020 2235 something
something okay
now this dependency is injected here in
the test controller so in the test
controller in the
user this got
injected test controller
one okay so now is there any more
dependency here no so now its post
construct will come so now it will write
test controller object hash code so it's
hash code and also I am writing user
hash code
so printing this so what it will print
test controller object hash code some
new hash code like say this is this
object hash code and we are also
printing this object hash code what
would be the same 1140 it will put the
same like 11 140 this this and this
would be same same user object it would
have right so currently only one object
of user is created one object
of test controller one is
created okay so this Constructor is done
eagly initialized now spring will say
okay is there any other class for which
I need to create eag initialized yes
test controller
two it will see that okay it is single
turn it can be do eagerly initialized so
what it will do is test controller to
instance
initialization test controller to
instance initialization
now the second step is inject the
dependency now it say that user so user
is single turn means only one object
would be created and it's already
created right so the same object would
be into the test controller 2 into the
user the same object would be
inserted the same object would be
inserted and after that it will out to
post construct as there are no more Auto
wi so test controller hash code some new
hash code for this one it's hash code
this object hash
code and for this user it would be like
the same this only so test controller
object hash code user is same so the
same
one so you got it like in a single turn
only one object is created per ioc
so this is just a different way of
telling a class that it's a single T and
when you start an application it is
eagly initialized and I have shown you
with an example that this is how
generally it resolves it if the object
is not created it will create and once
it is created the same object is used
everywhere and now if you invoking an
API let's say you are invoking this
fetch user API or fetch user 2 API
No Object construction will happen it
will simply invoke the particular API
all the objects are created before
itself we have
seen okay so single T is clear
right
cool now there is one other important is
something called prototype right so what
does prototype says that each time a new
object is created no matter if you are
if if a class is defined as prototype
new object is created each and every
time very simple another important part
very very important it's lazily
initialized it's not eagerly
initialized so what lazily initialized
means when object is
created or you can say that when object
is actually
needed actually needed then only
it would get
created okay so when object is actually
needed then only it get
created so I will explain you with this
simple example right so here test
controller one class this is a rest
controller so there are some apis I have
defined here so this is how the
Prototype you can do at theate scope and
you can use this enum configurable bean
factory scope prototype
right so this class has this two
injection dependencies one is user one
is a student let's see a student first
so a student is a component and there is
no scope means it
is single turn okay very simple class
and this student is dependent on user so
this is dependent on this
user Okay so and uh test controller is
also dependent on user so it is also
dependent on this user and what is this
user classes prototype so now see here I
have I can define a prototype like this
using enum or you can use even a string
like directly at uh prototype in double
codes okay so means user is prototype
class uh scope and test controller one
is also a prototype so means every time
a new object would be created for it a
student is single turn means only one
object would be created in the
system so now if I run the application
what would happen so now let's say if I
run the application what uh is ioc will
see that it will say okay rest
controller it would find it now it will
see its scope hey is it single turn no
it's a prototype prototype is lazily
initialized not at the time of
application startup so it will skip it
no I won't create its object until it's
not
used then it find let's say user hey
user is component it's scope is
prototype okay this is also lazily I
will not invoke it I will not create its
object then it will find a student okay
this is single T single T is eagly
initialized I can create it object so
first it will create a student instance
initialization so it will create student
instance
initialization and after this what would
happen is it will look for dependency
second step now the dependency is on
user so it has to be resolved right so
now user is prototype so now at this
time user object is created because it
is now it is required it is now
used right so
now user object would is
initialized user is initialized does
user has any dependency no so it post
construct would be called that uh its
Bean is properly constructed user hash
code some user hash code is got that
this is the user
object so this user object is now
injected
here now any more Auto no so now it post
construct will be involed a student
object hash code some hash code user
object so this is the user object would
be seeing here so this is student object
hash code and this user object which was
created this is what created right so
this is injected
here
okay till now all done right so now
application got rested
properly now what would happen let's say
you hit the API fetch user so fetch user
is here this API you hit now when you
invoke this API you know
that this object would be created by ioc
right so this is a prototype so means
ioc has to create a new object of test
controller right so it will create call
it Constructor test controller one
instance initialization
so till here we have seen application
started now we hit the
API so test controller one instance
initialization so what would happen
after
this it will look for dependency
resolution first
user so user is marked as
prototype I told you that prototype
means every time create a new object
even though user object is already
created and injected here in the student
but here now this is also again object
requested for in test controller new
object would be created so for
user user new object would be created so
with this hash code earlier when a
student created it was this hash code
right so now here if you see user is
created with different different object
is created for the
user okay why because it's a prototype
then a student student is single turn so
means only one object so it was eagerly
initialized so whatever the object was
con uh there it would get injected here
so whatever the hash code of student was
there the same ultimately got injected
here also so
20924 5685 so because it's a single turn
so same object is used in test
controller one depending
but for user a new object is constructed
not this one because it's a prototype
because user is prototype every time new
object is
constructed
right so you understand like every time
new object is constructed if you hit
this API can you just check one more
time if you hit another time fetch user
what would
happen if you hit another time what
would happen
since this class is marked as prototype
a new object would be constructed for
this so you will see one more like test
controller one instance initialization
one more object would be
created okay so prototype is very simple
every time new object is constructed and
it's lazily
initialized third is request this is
where ultimately confusion comes in
because that's where one more things
comes into the picture when I show you
this
part uh this proxy mode so this proxy
mode also comes into the picture here
and that's what make uh engineers get
confused with this request request is
scope so what does it
mean new object is created for each HTTP
request
for each HTTP request let's say fetch
user this is one HTTP request
Now new object will be created for all
the classes which are marked as
request right and if in this API if a
particular object is required four times
we will not create four objects only one
time okay let's see that with an example
and again it is laily initialized
so example is very simple again I have
created a test controller
class right so it has one this
API and I have marked it as
request this has two dependency one is
on user one is on student so let's see
uh user
first so user also I have marked as
request right so means for each HTTP
request a new object has to be created
no dependency on this
one and for a
student I called it as a prototype means
every time no matter what every time new
object should be
there and it has a dependency on
user so now let's see that when you
start an application what would happen
and when you invoke this HTTP API what
would happen how this uh dependency
resolution happen and the Scopes comes
into the
picture so when you start an application
ioc will look for all the component at
the rate rest controller and try to
create a bean so this it would find test
controller one scope is request so this
is lazy initialized nothing would happen
then it next goes to student it found
this at theate component scope is
prototype again a lazily initialized
nothing will happen then it will look
able to see user because it is marked as
atate component
but again its scope is also request
which is lazily initialized so no object
is created at the application startup so
at application startup here you see that
started spring boot application but no
object is
created okay makes sense now I am
hitting the API fetch user the first
time HTTP request is coming now HTTP
request is coming now what would happen
so it has to create an object so this is
request right so I called Fetch user so
now with for this HTTP request first
test controller object would be created
test controller
one test controller one instance
initialization okay this will get
printed then second it will look to
resolve the
dependency so it will goes to the user
user
first user is also marked as request so
means only one instance or new instance
should be created for each request so
for this request is there any user
request now no so it will create new
object user
initialization so user initialization
would happen any dependency no so post
construct would be user object hash code
so some hash code would get come
here okay so user will get injected here
after that it will resolve a
student student is prototype no matter
whether this same request different
request it new object has to be created
so
student student instance
initialization now it will go and
resolve the dependency it say that user
now here if you see that user is marked
as request one
object one object per request so one
object is already created so student
will use this no new object would be
created so student will use this
user right and student hash code so his
hash code will come and what would be
the user it it going to use this user
hash code so like
this so this is
the will uh expectation so test
controller initialization happen so test
controller ultimately goes to
our
user right so we have seen
that we have seen that user user object
created with this
one and this got injected into this test
controller now then student so student
is prototype so new instance would be
created and student is dependent on
user and user is marked as request right
so same object would be used right the
same thing is happening which we have
seen with
diagram so you got it
right and this ultimately the test
controller
has this
user and this student
object
okay so this is if this is clear if this
is clear the same thing is uh actually
printing in the logs
actually now what would happen if the
second time you are hitting the API when
the second time you are hitting the API
what would happen so till here this is
first
call right this is first
call now from
here now from
here second call
happening
this now when the second call happening
again I have also copy pasted the same
diagram here so that I don't have to
scroll much so this is request right so
now second request is coming so means a
new object would be created for this
one so it goes to again Auto user user
is again request a new object would be
created for this
one student student is anywh prototype
doesn't
matter right it will use it will create
a new object
itself so I'll show you that
first test controller instance
initialization so now here if you see
when I when I hit the second time it is
trying to create a new Bean for the test
controller one then it goes to the user
and it create a new object for the user
earlier was this now it's a different
object because user is marked as request
and this is a new HTTP
request then it goes to the student
student is prototype so no matter same
request
whatever new object would be
created right and then test
controller in the test controller we it
has an object and student right so now
here if you
see it has this
user and student also has the same user
so in the one request one HTTP request
no duplicate objects is created only one
time so test controller class student
class both wanted user object so user is
created only one time 8929 right the
same
8929 so both test controller and student
is using the same user
class okay and each HTTP
request a new object is
created I hope it's clear what does it
HTTP uh scope request
means now the problem comes in can you
answer me this one consider this below
request I have a test controller which I
marked as single
ton I have a class user which I marked
as scope
request so test controller one is
dependent on this
user what would
happen
Okay so our basic understanding now is
that single turn
is eagerly
initialized request scope
is lazy plus it is attached
with http P
request right attached with HTTP request
so when you start an
application so ioc will see that okay
rest controller this is single turn so I
can do legally initialize so it will try
to create its object so what it will do
is test controller one instance
initialization test controller one
instance
initialization now it will try to solve
this dependency It Go goes to the
user okay it say that hey user what is
your scope it say request is there any
during application start up is there any
active HTTP request is present no
because application is starting there is
no HTTP request so spring will not
create its object and that's why it will
get fail error creating
Bean because it won't be it uh so the
bean fail Bean creation fail for this
because this dependency is not resolved
because scope for this user is request
and request is tied up with an HTTP
request during eagerly
initialization application startup there
is no active HTTP request which it can
bound
to so how do you resolve this the
question comes if you have any class
which is singl turn and it wanted to ex
is or it has a dependency on a class
which is a scope
request how do you resolve this because
during Eagle initialization it will
fail so there is something called proxy
mode so in your user class which is
request scope is
request if you put a proxy mode like
let's
say a scope proxy mode target uncore
class so if you use this what you are
telling to Spring boot is that hey
create a proxy object at the time of
eagerly initialization even though there
is no HTTP request
present you can create one proxy object
of it like dummy object of a user and
use it for your object creation Bean
creation but when ultimately you going
to invoke me right then you can create a
real object and tied up with the HTTP
request so I'll show you with an example
now the same example but I have just
added proxy mode here and started the
application now what would happen ioc
will see this single turn test
controller one instance
initialization test controller one
instance
initialization now it has a dependency
on user so generally it should be like
user initialization printing right but
no this user is request scope it should
be with the HTTP request but I have put
a
proxy okay if there is no HTTP request
present create a dummy object so what it
would is create one dummy
object dummy user object and insert it
here inside a
user so here if you see there is no user
initialization call means user object is
not created but somehow dummy object got
inserted
into this one so it create inserted it
and then post construct here user object
some hash code comes so some dummy
object
created so this
success the bean creation of test
controller now got
success now when you hit this
API now when I'm hitting this API so now
this is one HTTP request
so now this API what would happen is
this actual dependency would get
resolved so now here if you see when I
hit this
API at this point of time it is actually
creating the user
initialization user initialization there
is no
dependency user object and now this user
object ultimately get inserted into h
here it
update so you got it like what is
request and there lot of confusion
happen with there so this request you
understood that it is always tied up
with HTTP request and if you are
trying to create it uh let's say you uh
single turn or
any application startup you are trying
to access this class you you have to use
proxy otherwise it would
fail then there is something called
session very very similar to http
request but only thing is object is
created for each HTTP session you know
that once HTTP session is created HTTP
session created you can call many HTTP
calls so HTTP request one HTTP request
two request three request four
so on till you don't end HTTP
session right so now it's not tied up
with each HTTP request one object is
created per each HTTP
session so it is lazily
initialized right and generally when
user access any endpoint right first
session is created
generally right and it's remain active
till it do not expires and you can so
there might be some default expire time
you can also configure the expire time
in the application. properties I think
there is some like sulet do
session. expiry sometime you can check
this one but there is certain property
which can tell which tell that this
session should get uh expired after this
time otherwise it's bring you some
default
time right
so I have created one test controller
one now I can you can use this scope
like this
session it is dependent on this
user so user is singl
ton right very
basic now what would happen when you
start an application so when you start
an
application this is lazily initialized
so session so nothing will happen for
this ioc will see that okay it is single
turn lazy initialization is possible so
user is
initialized there is no dependency so
user object hash code will also get
printed user initialized user hash code
printed now the first I am hitting this
fetch
user so I am hitting this so HTTP
session would get
created right the first time it is
creating so its object would created h
test controller one instance
initialization so test controller one
instance initialization till here we
have
seen after
that any dependency yes it has
dependency so it will see that okay this
is single turn only one object should
exist per ioc right so whatever the same
object that will get injected here and
then it will goes to the post
construct so test controller one hash
code and user hash code so whatever the
user hash code same would come here
because the same is got injected
here so test controller hash code
whatever the object is created and
inside this test controller the
dependency of user is the same one
because this is single turn one
n
okay now I am calling the API again same
so session is still running HTTP session
is created when you call the first time
so it is not yet ended so it is still in
running so now I call the fetch user
again so it is
session so it will not create new object
because this is just a new HTTP request
not a new session HTTP session is is
still valid it's not a new session so
will it create new object no it will not
create new object so it just call the
API No Object creation
happen now here in the third I am
calling logout API which ends this
session which end HTTP session so here
if you see this is the log out API I
have
called in this HTTP subet I specifically
uh get the session and make it
invalidate
manually right you can also automate it
using configuration but just to demo it
I manually invalidated it this
session so now in the log out I end the
session now I am calling the API again
what would happen now you are calling
the fetch user API again so now it will
create a new session again because there
is no session exist so new session again
mean new
test controller one instance
initialization here test controller one
instance initialization after ending new
object and this depend on user but user
is single ton so same singl ton object
would be used no new object should get
created so what initially user was
created right 619 it's the same because
it's a single turn but new object for
test controller is created because old
session was closed and new session is
started so you got it session also so
these are the main
Scopes and there is something called
application so application is like very
very similar to Singleton Singleton is
like one
object per
ioc application says
that one object
within different ioc let's say you you
there are three ioc are running ioc 1
ioc 2 ioc 3 there are three ioc's are
running to be
honest in this 9 years of experience I
haven't find out this use case like one
ioc is running at a time right but still
it's better to understand this when
multiple ioc's are running and you want
that only one object is shared among the
them then use
application right singl turnon just make
sure that in one ioc object uh only one
object is constructed application make
sure that one object across multiple
ioc's okay so but that's why I haven't
included it because I don't think it's
very much popular but yes it's better to
learn it but that's just my
opinion okay so see you guys I hope you
will find this useful please do share it
with your connection if you like it
thank you bye